Hello, everyone. I hope
you're all doing well,
and welcome to the next
lecture in our series
of lectures on renal
physiology. I think by
this time you have
hopefully have looked at
the functional anatomy and
the control of GFR and renal
blood flow and the variables
that regulate that, and
then are familiar with the
reabsorption of sodium and
water, and to a degree,
chloride, even if they didn't
spell it out, a lot of the
pathways for sodium and
chloride go hand in hand. But
today, we'll be talking about
more of the electrolytes that
are involved in physiology
and the role of the kidney
in their homeostasis.
So here are our
session objectives.
We're going to talk
about potassium.
We'll talk a little
bit about the renal
and angiotensin
-aldosterone system
and potassium
balance, acid base.
And it will, you know, that
we'll start talking about
acid base and how it affects
potassium homeostasis.
And then we'll finish off
by talking about calcium,
magnesium, and phosphate
in the nephron. And
you'll see that as we progress,
it becomes less complicated
when it comes to it,
but you can also imagine
the reason for the
complication is its importance.
So like in my previous
lectures, I'll
start off by a scenario,
a similar scenario
to one of the earlier
lectures I have.
Somebody, you know, you
have just spent your
last three summers
trying to get into shape.
You're running, you're
going to hot yoga, and one
day after a session of
hot yoga and jogging.
You leave the studio and
you feel like you're going
to fall down. You're
lightheaded and you feel your
heart fluttering in your chest
and you don't know what's
going on. And your instructors
are on top of everything,
immediately give you
some coconut water and a
banana and you sit there
and you drink your coconut
water and after five minutes
you feel great and you
wonder this is magic what is
in coconut water and bananas
that can work so quickly
and make you feel better
so this is what basically
the scenario we're
talking about and hopefully
by the end of this lecture,
we can address a possible
solution to this.
So we'll start talking
again. We're talking about
the nephron, and you already
have discussed water,
sodium, and I said to a
degree of chloride, and today
we'll talk about these
players, potassium, calcium,
magnesium, and phosphate,
and then the next lecture
we'll talk about the rest
of these players and these
compounds. But today's
our electrolytes, our non
-bicarbonate electrolytes.
And again, we reiterated the
important player here
is the nephron and
the kidney keeps a
very, very tight watch
on, on these electrolytes.
And, you know,
we've already stated,
the kidney filters and
then reabsorbs, and it
can also filter, secrete,
and it also can filter,
reabsorb, and secrete.
So all three of these
major functions are going
on, sometimes simultaneously,
in order to give us
excretion and whatever
is left in the
urine. And it's a
very simple algebraic
relationship. So
excretion is basically
filtration minus
reabsorption plus secretion.
You can put numerical
values if you want
to figure it out
again, but it's very
algebraic, nothing
complicated about it.
In general, we can say
that reabsorption is much
more quantitatively more
important than tubular
secretion. There's much
more reabsorption going on
than there is secretion.
You can just see very few
compounds or physiological
compounds are secreted,
only potassium, protons,
and to a degree urea.
We can talk about having
physiological purposes.
Drugs get secreted
either because we want to
get rid of them. Urinary
excretion of drugs is
one of the major pathways
of drug metabolism.
Also, sometimes you need
to have drugs get into the
nephron for it to have an
effect. So diuretics are very
important because you need
them to get into the lumen
for them to have their
activity. And antibiotics,
you know, for any kind of
infection, you need to get
urine, you need to get
the drug into the urinary
compartment in order for it
to have, be most efficacious.
And some of our electrolytes
are highly absorbed, 99
to 100 percent are absorbed
because of the role of
the kidney and what's
happening inside the kidney.
Start off with one of
the most important ones,
potassium. And potassium
balance and the renal regulation
of potassium should be
one of those important
things that as medical
students you should familiar
familiarize yourself with
um you get electrolyte panel
chem sevens potassium is
always there it's very very
important and i would
like you to think about it
one of the first things you
want to look at is always
potassium with almost
any kind of diagnosis or
chief complaint that comes
in because changes in
potassium homeostasis can
have such widespread effects.
You've seen something
like this before, you
know that we have a huge,
we have a very large
difference in
intercellular versus
extracellular potassium. It's
the opposite relationship
to that of sodium
and chloride, right?
You know, we have low
amounts of potassium outside,
high amounts of potassium
inside the cell. And this
extracellular potassium is
very, very tightly maintained.
In fact, it can be outside
of normal range, even by
tenths of a millimolar,
can be considered dangerous
acutely. Even chronically,
it can lead to
a variety of metabolic
disturbances. So
I have in these three
tables how changes in
the different compartments
can affect cell
function and generalized
effects. So, for
example, if we decrease
intracellular calcium,
cells will shrink.
If we increase
intracellular potassium,
did I say calcium?
I meant potassium.
If we increase
intracellular potassium,
cells will swell. They
can have different
effects on DNA protein
synthesis and growth.
You have decreased
intracellular potassium,
you'll get a reduction
and a slowing of growth.
Increases in intercellular
potassium, their
effects are not as clear,
but definitely hypo,
that's actually wrong
terminology, decreases in
intercellular potassium can
cause reduction in growth. If
you change the ratios, it
can have effects, but, you
know, but changes in
extracellular potassium also
can have a wide variety of
effects. So, for example,
decreasing extracellular
potassium hypokalemia can
result in acidosis, it can
cause constriction of blood
vessels, so you can actually
become hypertensive.
Neuromuscular-wise, you
can get muscle weakness,
paralysis, and if, you
know, the decrease in muscle
failure, you can have
respiratory failure and abdominal
distension. And, you know,
if you've ever seen pictures
of children in famine zones,
you'll always see them
with distended bellies, and
part and parcel of what's
responsible for the distended
bellies that one sees
in these children is
the loss, is the chronic
hypokalemia that they're in
because of the lack of food.
Hyperkalemia, increasing
your potassium,
stimulates activity
and excitability, but
too much of that is a
good thing. You can,
too much contraction,
too much constriction can
actually lead to flaccid
paralysis. You get to a
point that it's firing
off so many signals that
the muscles stop
responding to it.
And again, very important.
Oh, so very important in
cardiac activity. This is
what can kill you acutely.
Changes in extracellular
potassium have to be
tightly controlled and
addressed because the
effects on electrophysiology
in the heart can be
dramatic and again can
cause fatal arrhythmias.
And in the last one,
I have an effect,
the effects of
changing the ratios,
either by increasing,
for example,
extracellular potassium,
that decreases the
ratio, right, because
you're increasing the
denominator. You can
cause depolarization and
hyperactivity. And if you
increase that ratio, right,
you know, it's, say, by
increasing intracellular
potassium, you can
cause hyperpolarization.
Hyperpolarization makes
excitable cells less able to
respond to a stimulus. So
cells can't reach the threshold
to activate an action
potential. And it's very
important in excitable cells,
cells that respond to electrical
activity, or cells that
have automaticity, that have
the ability to initiate
their own action potential.
And increasing the ratio of
intracellular to extracellular
potassium is a very good
way to tamp that down.
Homeostasis is,
again, we get most of our
potassium through our diet.
Part of it gets
excreted as part of our
food, the majority
of it gets absorbed,
and once absorbed, it
gets shunted to different
tissues, and the rest of it
is filtered into kidney and
what's left comes out of
the urine then the lion's
share of potassium is it
can be found in our muscle
cells skeletal muscles
smooth muscle cardiac
muscle about 75 percent of
the total amount of potassium
in our body is found in
muscle cells which is
very very you know which which
which becomes understandable
when you see it if you
have massive amounts
of muscle damage you know
if you have damage to
skeletal muscle if you have
a crush injury or if in some
cases of rhabdomyolysis
one of the first things
you want to take a look at
is potassium you know the
plasma potassium levels
and how to approach that.
Any kind of hemolytic
activity also becomes
important in potassium
amounts in the plasma,
and you put the two of
them together, which
you really see in
traumatic and injuries. You
can see why it becomes
very, very important.
The gut plays a small role
in potassium excretion,
a very small role in
response to either adrenal
hormones, increases in
potassium intake, or when
you have situations where
your kidneys have lost
their abilities to
excrete potassium. So in
people who have renal disease
or are on their way to
renal failure and they
can't excrete potassium,
the GI tract tries to
pick up some of the slack.
It doesn't work. It
fails because eventually
the ceiling for their
effect is very limited.
And as we said before,
internal potassium
balance is really,
really important for
cell function. And you
don't need a little to
cause a dramatic, you only
need a little bit of a
shuttle between intracellular
to extracellular
to have really large
effects on extracellular
potassium. And these
changes can have severe
consequences for cardiac
and neuromuscular function.
So let's talk about
the big picture. What
happens, you know, when
we are faced with a large
potassium load.
And I will do the simplest,
easiest way possible.
If you have eaten a lot
of food that has potassium
in it, let's say you sat
down and you know you had
six bananas and you washed
it down with four glasses
of coconut water. Don't
do that, that's really
sounds horrible, but you
know what I'm trying to say.
You can see that, you
know, and I've marked this
in these two graphs. Then
you can take a look at
this in terms of the
temporal sequence. The y-axis
or the x-axis is in
hours, so the first bar
is one hour. And you
can see that within
minutes, once you take a
large plasma, you know,
a large potassium load
and it gets absorbed,
you have a very, very initial
high and fast increase
in plasma concentration.
This happens within minutes,
and then it starts coming
down. It starts coming down
because around the same time
that the plasma levels go
up, the cells start shunting
potassium into the cells.
That takes a little bit
longer, but you maximize it at
after about an hour. By
two hours you've reached a
maximum and then you start
seeing the levels come down.
And that decrease is
at the same time
that your body starts
getting rid of the
extra potassium.
So again, the regulation
is very, very tight. You
see that within two hours
of having a high load
of potassium, you've almost
decreased the increase
in, you've cut down on
the increase by like
almost 50%, and it's down
to a basal, almost basal
levels by three hours.
So you can see that the
importance is to keep it
very, very, very tight.
And what stimulates
these movements, it's
really by most of the
actions of different
hormones. A couple of the
most important ones in
the direct regulation of
physiological increases
of potassium are
insulin and aldosterone.
And both of them will
enhance the movement of
extracellular potassium to
intercellular potassium by our
old friend, the sodium
-potassium ATPase. Remember,
sodium-potassium ATPase
takes three potassiums,
puts them inside the cell,
translocates them inside
the cell, takes two moles
of sodium, pushes them
outside the cell, and I'm
sorry, the opposite. Three
sodiums go outside the
cell, two potassiums go
inside the cell, and one
molecule of ATPase is used.
Insulin, how it goes,
how it increases is
after every meal, we
get a spike in insulin,
not only because of the
increase in sugars, but
also because of the
increase in potassium.
The increase in
potassium will depolarize
pancreatic beta cells,
and the depolarization of
pancreatic beta cells
stimulates insulin release.
Same stimulus will also
cause depolarization of cells
in the adrenal glomerulosa,
the source of aldosterone,
and that will stimulate
aldosterone release.
Epinephrine, physiologically,
we don't have any epinephrine.
There is no change in epi
-secretion in physiological
changes in potassium.
Epinephrine is a stress hormone,
a product of the adrenal
medulla. So you have it only
in situations where you have,
where there is a metabolic
stress involved. In those
cases, if you have a
pathophysiological increase
in potassium, you get an
increase in epi secretion and
this increase in epi secretion
will stimulate the you
know the the translocation
of of potassium you know
um stress responses if you
want to think of the scenario
where they couldn't be
important any kind of an
injury if you have for example
again a crush injury you're
in pain your epi levels are
sky high and this is one of
the ways that the body was
going to respond to the
stress of an injury is by
making sure that potassium
levels are tightly regulated.
One of the bigger
controllers and
manipulators of
potassium homeostasis
are states of our
acid-base balance.
So what are, we'll start
off by looking at acidosis,
is how can changes in
acid-base balance in
the body affect internal
potassium distribution.
So if you are
undergoing acidosis,
and remember acidosis
is a process.
So you are undergoing
acidosis to become acidemic,
right? So acidemia is a
state of high acidity. Well,
acidosis is the process
that leads to high acidity.
Again, this is just
language and nomenclature.
So we'll start off
here. So if we have high
amounts of potassium,
of protons, right?
High levels of protons will
give us lower pH, right?
So what happens if we have
high amounts of protons
in the plasma? Well, it
does two things. First
two targets that it can
act are, and we'll talk
about the larger storage
of potassium in muscle
cells. It affects two
different transporters.
It can affect
the sodium proton
antiporter, and I have this
under A, and it can affect
the sodium bicarbonate
co-transporter.
How does it do that?
Well, if you have excess
protons, the excess
protons will inhibit the
activity by actually
causing a block for the
efflux of protons by
mass action. Just by
having more of them in
there, this is blocked.
So if the movement
of protons out of the
cell is blocked by
excess protons, and
it's basically holding
the door shut. Then
sodium also will not
go inside the cell.
What about it
affecting bicarbonate?
Well, then it'll just
bind with bicarbonate
to give you carbonic
acid, H2CO3.
H2CO3, we'll talk about it
in acid-base balance, is
a substrate and it gets
metabolized in the plasma.
So if we remove this, we
also will block the activity
of the co-transporter,
so sodium will not go in.
Sodium doesn't go
in, bicarb doesn't go
in, it blocks the
removal of protons.
And this lack of
sodium influx will give
us a, eventually
cause a decrease in
intercellular sodium. If you
have low intercellular sodium,
the substrate for the sodium
potassium ATPase is not
there, so you don't have any
more potassium being taken
from outside the cell and
taken into inside the cell.
So that becomes an issue.
Another effect of the
increase in intracellular
protons as a consequence
of the effects on the
co-transporters and
the counter and the
antiporter is it'll drive
off potassium of any
protein that it's bound to.
And what it does, these
proteins become protonated,
driving off potassium,
and then potassium
will then leak out of
the cell via potassium
channels. And in its last
effect, an increase in
acidity, an increase in
protons, will block this
sodium-potassium-2
-chloride co-transporter
that is found on a variety
of different tissues.
All of them, the net
result is being severe
electrolyte abnormalities
when we have
acidosis. So, what are
the net effects is,
right? If we don't have
sodium going in, we can't
have sodium going out,
and if we don't have
sodium going out, we can't
have potassium coming in.
put that in combination
of this co-transporter,
and what you end up is
having is hyperkalemia.
So acidosis becomes a
big driver of potassium
imbalance by promoting
hyperkalemia.
What do you think is going
to happen in alkalosis?
And if we were in
one room, I would
say raise your hand
and win a cookie.
You're not going to win
a cookie. The opposite of
this is also true. So if
you have alkalemia, right,
undergoing alkalosis, this
causes the cells to take up
potassium, and a consequence
of that will be hypokalemia.
How does that happen?
Well, here now we have the
pH going up. pH goes up,
what's going to happen to our
bicarb levels that means
they're elevated this is why
we look at bicarb levels
when we have our electrolytes
become very very important
if our bicarb levels are
elevated what's going to
happen to what's going to
happen to our our antiporter.
Well, now instead of
blocking, it's going to bind
with the proton to give you
carbonic acid. It's
going to keep sucking
out protons. More sodium
is going to go in.
What is it going to do
to the co-transporter?
Well, now we have a higher
concentration outside.
It's going to drive
bicarb in, and if bicarb
goes in, sodium goes
in. And this is simple.
Once you increase
sodium, you'll increase
the availability for
sodium-potassium ATPase
by increasing the substrate,
and then potassium
is pushed into the cell.
So alkalosis increases
in bicarb can give you
hypokalemia, right?
So potassium influx will
give you hypokalemia
as a consequence of
increased bicarb.
and this also uh this
is a bi-directional
relationship right
because uh the opposite
is also true so
hypokalemia can cause
alkalosis and hyperkalemia
can cause acidosis
so um that's the big picture
how about at the level
of the nephron um so here
are some general generalities
about what happens to the
potassium in the nephron.
As you can see, the majority
of it is reabsorbed from
a filtered load of around
810 millimolars per day.
Not all of it is reabsorbed.
A good amount is
secreted, depending on the
condition. So we have
a small amount getting
excreted, more than sodium.
So there's a little bit
more regulation involved
in potassium than it
is sodium. So, and it's
very, very straightforward,
right? If you have
a lower normal diet,
kidneys can achieve this
very easily, can maintain
potassium in low and normal
diet conditions by adjusting
filtration and reabsorption.
However, if you take a
lot of potassium, then your
kidneys must start to get
rid of them. And that's
when excretion becomes a
really big part of a potassium
balance. Again, under
normal conditions, not so
much, but when we have chronic
high intake, secretion
becomes very, very important.
So the handling is a
combination of filtration,
reabsorption, and secretion.
So where do we have these
things occurring? Well,
filtration obviously occurs at
the level of Bowman's capsule.
The proximal convoluted tubule
absorbs around 80% of the
filtered load of potassium.
A little bit of it is
reabsorbed in the descending,
the thin descending loop
of Henle. But the majority,
the biggest proportion
outside of the
proximal convoluted
tubule occurs at the
level of the gayscending
loop of Henle.
Very little in the distal
collecting tubule and
some in the cortical
and medullary collecting
ducts but that's under
low or normal conditions
but if you have normal
high right some of the
extremes really no very
little effect on the
proximal tubule and
on the thin descending
loop tubule but uh
you start having uh
secretion in the distal
convoluted tubule and the
connecting tubule and
the medullary, yeah,
the medullary and cortical
collecting tubules.
So secretion becomes
very important in
normal high as opposed to
low normal concentration
of dietary intake of
dietary potassium.
So let's start off at
the top after filtration.
Once, you know, once the
ultrafiltrate is made
in the Bowman's capsule.
The first area that the
electrolytes will see
is the proximal tubule.
So potassium is reabsorbed
by two paracellular
mechanisms in proximal
tubules. So the forces are
electrochemical and then
straightforward chemical. The
electrochemical force
is the lumen positivity,
the transepithelial voltage
that one finds in the
change in transepithelial
voltage one finds in the
proximal tubule. Initial
parts of the proximal
tubule, the lumen, the urine
is more negative compared
to the basolateral side,
but that decreases as
more and more electrolytes
are absorbed. So by the
time you get to the bottom
of the proximal tubule,
and again, to the proximal
convoluted tubule, to the
initial parts of the proximal
straight tubule, you have
a highly positive intraluminal
membrane potential.
And this electromotor force
pushes potassium out by
parasite, via the paracellular
pathways indicated here.
The other one is a concept
called solvent drag, which
water will, that the more
flow you have, the more it
just piggybacks on water,
on the movement of water
through paracellular pathways.
So this concept is called
solvent drag, and it's a
big driver in diffusion of
solutes in trans-epithelial,
trans-capillary exchanges.
So, also, another way that
they control potassium
is by the actions of a
potassium channel called the
renal outer medullary
potassium channel. That's
where it was first
characterized. that's why they
called it renal outer
medullary potassium channel
since the discovery it's
been found in a lot of
other places and now it's
defined by its name inwardly
rectifying potassium
channels but you see this
designation all the time
so they're the same thing
so rom k channels that's
much easier to say than
inwardly rectifying
especially when you're wearing
Invisalign and you're lisping
everything, so I'm going
to say ROMK. We have expression
of ROMK on both luminal
and basolateral sides
that causes the leaking of
potassium from the
intracellular compartment into
extracellular compartment.
There's more of them on the
basolateral side. So in terms
of the quantity of the number
of cells here, I mean, this
is obviously a schematic.
You'll have more of them,
so you have more of a
flux going into the
basolateral side. And the last
component of it is the
potassium chloride co
-transporter that's involved
in the efflux of potassium.
Most important section
of the nephron for the
reabsorption of
potassium is the thick
-ascending limit. And it
does so by the sodium
-potassium 2-chloride
cotransporter, the NKCC.
And this is a very, very
important cotransporter in
the nephron. Now, what
happens, the nephron by this
point is highly positive.
The luminal side is more
positive compared to the
interstitial side. This
electropositivity will
push sodium and chloride
through parasailor pathways
into the interstitial space.
Additionally, the sodium
chloride, sodium potassium
to chloride co-transporter
will take one mole
of sodium, one mole of
chloride and two moles, one
mole of potassium and two
moles of chloride and co
-transports them together
to the inside of the cell.
Now, obviously, two of
them are going down their
concentration gradient.
Sodium chloride, potassium is
going against this
concentration gradient. So you
need the electromotive
force that's developed by
the sodium potassium ATPase
to maintain the differences
in concentration gradient
that are integral to
the use, to the functionality
of this co-transport.
So once the potassium goes
out, it'll start coming out
again, either on the luminal
side or on the basolateral
side via the ROMK channel.
Now what happens here is
the potassium that leaks
out then just basically will
start getting recycled
through the NKCC. And you can
see how this recycling feeds
into the lumen positivity,
because the top part, if we
don't have this recycling,
this is an electrically
neutral transferring, right?
So there is two positives,
two negatives, so zero
difference in charge. But if
the potassium is recirculating,
recycling, then you have
loss of two chlorides and
the loss of only one sodium,
so you'll have more positivity
on the outside. So you
can see that this system
kind of feeds into itself,
promotes its own usefulness.
See how I actually think
this is a really elegant
little system, this the
recycling, to maintain not
only the appropriate
concentration, but to use
them to save something
that you need. And then the
other portions of potassium
are then reabsorbed and
then taken back into the
interstitium through the
rom-K channel on the
basolateral side. Why is
this important? Well,
because this guy is a target.
It's a target of the
class of diuretics
we call the loop
diuretics. They're
also called high
ceiling diuretics.
Because once you
disrupt it, you
end up losing a lot of sodium,
potassium, chloride,
and along with it water.
So it's got to have very
high potential for diuresis.
What happens in the
collecting duct?
Similar, but some
different players.
The collecting tubules
got cells that are called
principal cells, and
their major function
is the secretion of
potassium into the lumen.
The other important
transporter that
they have is an
epithelial sodium channel
called, again by
its initials, ENAC.
ENAC is found in the principal
cells of the collecting tubule.
These are, and the other
population of cells
are called the intercalated
cells. The majority
of the cells of the
collecting duct are principal
cells, minorities around
intercalated cells.
You majority of it occurs
in principal cells.
So what happens here?
Well, here, again,
the movement, you know,
by the time you get here,
our potential is more negative.
So instead of pushing
things out, it will start
holding on to any kind
of a positive ion,
or using it sort of as
a magnet to pull it in.
If you're asking me,
well, Dr. Ascari,
why doesn't it do
that to sodium?
I'm going to tell you
what I tell everybody.
I don't know. No,
I'm only joking.
The reason is that the
concentration gradient,
the chemical force for
driving sodium, the low
intercellular sodium
compared to outside, is a
stronger driving force
than this transepithelial
voltage, so you'll have more
of a pushing action than
you have of holding
anything back. However, it
does act as a magnet for
potassium. In this case,
once you, you know,
this is, you You know,
you don't really lose
that much as you're
going into, you know,
your cells become,
your lumen doesn't
become positive,
right? It becomes
more negative.
And the reason is this
exchange is neutral, right?
One positive goes in, one
positive goes out. You
need to have this electrical
neutrality in order to
have a function of the
efficient function of ENAC.
Again,
sodium potassium ATPase is
important for creating the
environment where potassium
can come in and then
recycle like it did before
to kind of give us a constant
back and forth, while
maintaining the high
potassium inside, so
it can be secreted into
the luminal, into the
luminal compartment.
In the collecting
tubules, you'll
have different populations.
So you have
intercalated cells, and
the intercalated
cells have two types,
type A or alpha or type
B beta. This is one
of the few times that
they go interchangeably.
A lot of the times when
you see alpha, beta, A, B
designations, they're very
unique to those systems.
This is one of the times
that they go back and forth.
So what's important here?
Well, type A intercalated
cells are very, very
important, or alpha
intercalated cells of a
primary role in the secretion
of protons, while beta
intercalated cells are
integral for the
reabsorption of bicarbonate.
I have put a schematic of
both of them. It's, you
can see that, you know,
ultra structurally, they're
a little bit different.
they have these huge
brush borders, you can see
the distinction between
them under electron microscope.
But in this context,
we can just look at them
as one set of cells.
So the difference is where
these, where these
things occur.
The secretion of protons
occurs at the luminal
side via an HK, a
hydrogen potassium pump.
There, we need the pump
because we are pulling
in potassium against
its concentration
gradient, and at the
same time losing protons.
The X, and there is a leakage
of protons also in this
context via them, via a
ATPase, a hydrogen ATPase.
So two different
molecules, two different
molecules using ATP,
but one does with
bringing in potassium
against its concentration
gradient, the other one
is pushing potassium
across the plasma membrane.
Again, the gradient
is built by the sodium
-potassium ATPase.
In beta cells, you have
an antiporter, a chloride
bicarbonate antiporter,
and you have, of
course, our old friend,
the ROMK channel. This is
where they first discovered
it, right? And so
the reabsorption
of potassium occurs
by the HK ATPase, right,
by bringing potassium
in from the lumen and
then driving potassium
out by its concentration
gradient using the
ROM-K channel. So you
can see that this is,
you know, these pathways kind
of will lead into each other
and becomes very,
very important
when you have
hypokalemic alkalosis.
So what else can modulate
potassium secretion in the
distal circuitry system? Well,
you can have factors that
are in the lumen. So big
players are sodium and water.
So increases in flow rate,
if you have increases in
sodium, if you have increases
in water, you will have,
you will stimulate
potassium secretion,
right? Because we
have more sodium goes
through ENAC, potassium
gets secreted.
Inhibitors look obviously if
you have too much potassium,
right?
So if you have too much
potassium you're not going
to be needing stimulation
or secretion right if
it's high in the lumen then
you don't want any more
to go in diuretics are
really a big player diuretics
can cause in the lumen
luminal diuretics can
cause the loss of potassium
by enhancing secretion.
You know, peritubular
factors, things that are in
between, obviously, if you
have high potassium inside
peritubular interstitial
blood, you're going to want to
get rid of your potassium.
Any kind of an intake,
increases in intake, increases
in potassium by injury,
you know, increases in pH, all
of them will cause increases
in secretion.
A little bit, right, and
then potassium secretion
in the collecting ducts,
you know, occurs by
diffusion from the
principal cells, and again,
electrical chemical
gradient becomes important.
If we have an increase
in luminal sodium.
This will enhance
apical sodium entry
through ENAC. ENAC
will depolarize.
Cells go, you know,
sodium going in through
ENAC will depolarize
the cell and it becomes
more positive and that
pushes potassium out,
right? So this function
will push potassium
out. And if you have
something that blocks this
apical channel, which
you have in a class of
diuretics called potassium
-sparing diuretics,
ameloride triamterine,
they will inhibit the
movement of sodium and
hence the loss of potassium.
and there are other
situations if you replace
aluminum chloride with anions
that are not as reabsorbed
as readily as chloride
are mainly toward larger
size right this you know
the peritubular is not
a big gate these are very
small spaces so if you
have larger anions they
just will not go through.
So they can affect
lumen negativity
and changes in
potassium transport.
So now we talk a little
bit about renin-angiotensin
system. I've spoken to
about it before, but in this
context, we really only are
going to talk about this
wing of it. I mentioned
before, aldosterone is a major
part of the renin-angiotensin
-aldosterone system.
It is a product of
the renal cortex.
And in the renin-angiotensin
system, it is released
upon stimulation by angiotensin
II. And angiotensin 2
will act on its receptor,
angiotensin AT2 receptor and
AT1 receptors, and stimulate
the release of mineralocorticoid
receptor, which will
enhance sodium reabsorption
and potassium excretion.
It does so in principal
cells of the collecting
duct, and it does that by not
only increasing the activity,
but also increasing the
number of the sodium-potassium
ATPase. The activity is
initial, so there's a
phosphorylation event that
aldosterone will stimulate
to increase its activity, and
then after a while, because
it is a steroid receptor
and FX gene transcription,
you start getting the creation
of new proteins and
insertion of the protein into
the basolateral side of
collecting of principal cells.
The other product
of the adrenal
cortex are the glucocorticoids.
And glucocorticoids,
again, their stress,
they get released upon to
maintain carbohydrate
metabolism along with a
lot of other different
physiological functions.
Natural and synthetic
glucocorticoids can
enhance potassium excretion
by increasing flow,
water, and sodium along
the collecting tubules.
It does also, you know,
not only water and
flow, but also
increasing GFR. So all of
them will lead to
availability of sodium in
water and then enhancing
potassium loss.
So unphysiologically
high glucocorticoids,
either when you're
taking medication
for a variety of
different conditions,
glucocorticoids are
one of our big guns.
It acts the mineralocorticoid
receptor. It's a
complex biology. I don't expect
you to know the intricate
details. ****, most people
don't even understand
it. but this is all you have
to know is unphysiologically
high glucocorticoids
will stimulate potassium.
If you want to know the
gross details, I will
gladly enlighten you and
I can sit down and show
you the breakdown, but you
don't need to know it as
just for your own curiosity.
I can tell you that,
but there's very few people
know the gross details.
Alright, that was potassium.
So the next series
of slides are going to
be talking about calcium.
Now calcium, just as
potassium, is incredibly
important in a variety
of different enzymatic
pathways, and like
potassium, its levels are
tightly controlled. Unlike
potassium, the majority
of calcium stores in our
body is in our bones.
There, it's bound to phosphate
in the form of hydroxyapatite.
And calcium and phosphate
balance goes hand
in hand because the
source is the same.
And we really try to
keep the formation and
removal from the plasma
into this physiological
process under very,
very tight control.
Again,
we, you know, most of the
calcium we get is through
our diet. We want to keep
it tight. And what we
lose is basically what
we get. The rest of it is
all under tight control
where do we find calcium
well you can they're
either ionized free calcium
it's bound to proteins
and which proteins you
might ask well mostly
it's bound to albumin
albumin has got a lot
of different you know um
binding sites high
affinity low affinity
for a number of
different compounds
It's also bound to alpha
and beta globulins,
and it's bound to
clotting factors.
In fact, a good way for
anti-clotting is to chelate
calcium, to remove calcium
from any kind of a biological
media. You can see immediate
loss of ability to clot.
uh so protons compete with
calcium to to uh negative
sites on small proteins or
small molecules so again the
rate you know in when we
have acidosis or alkalosis
we can um change plasma
potassium levels right potassium
levels will go up if you
have acidosis you have too
much H, it'll push calcium
off these sites into the
free ionized form. Alkalosis
does the exact opposite.
And in fact, acute
alkalosis, the signs and
symptoms are very much
like hypocalcemia.
And, you know, hypercalcemia is
you'll get a lot of excitable,
hyperexcitability from cells
that ability to be excited
so we're talking about
neurons muscle cells and
hypercalcemia will cause a
depression of that um i had used
improper terminology in
this slide that i presented
to you so if you're
looking at this and reading
my uh and and reading
the lecture i apologize
but this is a more
appropriate term for what I
was trying to convey in
the first version of it.
So, two-thirds of
filtered calcium is
reabsorbed in the
proximal tubule. Remember,
everything is absorbed
iso-osmotically, so
the concentration
doesn't really change.
the majority of it is
reabsorbed in the thick
ascending limb some of
it is reabsorbed in the
distal collecting duct
and the rest of it is
reabsorbed in in the in
the cortical and measuring
collecting ducts this
reabsorption in the
proximal tubule it is not
subject to any control
and it occurs via paracellular
roots remember our
intraluminal transmembrane
potential is is
positive, and this positivity
will push calcium through
paracellular drag,
either by diffusion or by
solvent drag. Very much
a non-regulated process.
It's got high permeability,
whatever those
junctions are, they
love, they love calcium.
And obviously the higher
the sodium flow is
reabsorption and if you
decrease reabsorption you
decrease calcium reabsorption
and if you decrease
calcium reabsorption
you'll have excess calcium
in your urine you'll
get calciuria. So this
paracellular reabsorption
is very much dependent on
water and salt. So water
reabsorption, too much
water, you have calciuria,
you have hypocalciuria,
you have more
calcium reabsorption,
hypocalcium, right? Yeah.
And the opposite of that,
if you have a salt load by
decreasing sodium and
water reabsorption.
In the tau, in the thick
ascending limb, where you
have the majority of
calcium reabsorption, This
also occurs passively via
paracellular root, and it's
completely dependent on
the potassium recycling
that one sees in combination
of ROM-K and the NKCC.
This positive lumen
will push calcium from
paracellular roots into
the substancial space.
The other pathway that's very
important in this context
is the calcium sensing
receptor. Calcium sensing
receptor is found in,
you'll hear more about it in
endocrine, but once calcium
concentration reaches a
certain level, it can start
acting as an agonist on
this receptor, the calcium
sensing receptor. And the
higher the calcium, the more
prone it is to stimulate
this receptor, and And
stimulation of this receptor
will cause an inhibition
of the ROMK and NKCC. If we
block these two, we will
lose the lumen positivity
of the nephron. and if we
lose the lumen positivity,
we end up losing the impetus
for calcium to get reabsorbed.
How about in the distal
convoluted tubules?
About 8 percent of the filtered
load of calcium is reabsorbed.
It's an important site
despite the small amounts, and
it's not paracellular it's
transcellular and it does so
by a couple of different
transporters by three
transporters actually so calcium
will enter the cell via these
calcium channels called trp
v5 and v6 this is on the
luminal side so calcium
will enter the cell by these
biluminal calcium
channels. Once they're
inside the cell, they're
either exchanged for
sodium by this sodium
-calcium counter
transporter, which takes
molecules of calcium.
It will be,
take calcium and exchange
it with sodium using the
concentration gradient of
sodium to drive out calcium.
And it'll also get pushed
out by a calcium ATPase,
which takes one molecule
of calcium and replaces
it with two molecules of
protons using up one ATP.
So if we have low
extracellular calcium,
we won't have too much of a
substance, you know,
we will have low
NCX activity, and then this
ATPase becomes
this major pathway.
But the counter, the bi
-directional exchanger
becomes very important
when calcium in
the plant, when you
have hypercalcemia. So,
normal calcium regulation,
the calcium, the ATPase,
but higher amounts of
calcium, you start getting
involvement of the
bidirectional exchanger.
So, magnesium, a lot
of, it's very similar
to calcium in terms
of its regulation.
You can find a lot of it
with bone, even though it's
not a component of hydroxyapatite.
It's not chemically
linked to hydroxyapatite,
but it is found in bone.
And a lot of the diffusible
magnesium complexes
outside in the plasma
are bound to phosphates,
to citrates, to
oxalates, other anions.
And if whenever we have
any kind of a disturbance
of magnesium metabolism,
we really are talking about
abnormal loss. I can't
think of a situation where
you can have hypermagnesemia,
even though I'm
sure there are some, but,
you know, I mean, oh,
actually, not because of
excess intake, but mostly
because of renal failure. I
can't think of a situation
where you can have a lot
of excess intake unless
it is a toxicological
situation. I can't think of
any kind of a physiological
situation where you
can take a lot of magnesium.
Again, it's got a, I
would imagine, but if I'm
wrong, please correct me.
It's one of those things.
A lot of the times when you
have loss is because
either you have diarrhea, a
lot of fluid loss, you have
lack of GI absorption or
diuretics or issues with the
kidney if you have excess
diuresis or lack of diuresis.
The clinical manifestations
are mostly neurological
disturbances, especially,
again, if you have hypolevels,
cardiac arrhythmias,
and increases in peripheral
resistance. In fact,
magnesium is a very
good supplement to
take if you have
blood pressure issues.
They're not the most expensive
things, but they promote
flow, and they are very,
you know, they vasodilate,
and magnesium is good for
healthy blood vessels.
Where do we have
magnesium transport in the
nephron? Well, we have
them in three places,
proximal tubule,
the case sending
limb, and distal
collecting tubule.
Again,
it's paracellular in
the proximal tubule,
driven by the positivity
of the internal
the luminal voltage, again, by
either solvent drag
or by diffusion.
And like calcium, again,
the activity of
potassium recycling will
give us the lumen
positivity that pushes
magnesium into the
interstitial compartment,
and then in the distal
convoluted tubule,
you actually have
mechanisms to control the
concentrations, mostly
by it piggybacking
the same channel that
we saw with calcium.
It uses TRPM, one of
the calcium channels.
It'll piggyback it
and get inside the
cell, and then it jumps
on the NKCX to get
out of the cell into
the basolateral side.
This process is
stimulated by EGF
receptor, epidermal
growth factor receptor.
This is an interesting
receptor. If you've
ever done work with
it, you can see it's
ubiquitous. It can
interact with a variety of
different other receptors
and transporters.
It's called EGF receptor
because that's where they
first discovered it in response
to looking for epidermal
growth factor. And then
once you find more and more
things, you find the
interactions. So it's just not
a growth factor. It's a
major regulator of changes.
So what regulates
magnesium reabsorption?
Well,
you can, as I said,
like EGF does that. And
here are some of the
factors affecting magnesium
reabsorption. Volume
contraction can increase
magnesium reabsorption
in the proximal tubule.
Obviously, volume expansion can
decrease magnesium
reabsorption.
PTH, calcitonin, glucagon,
metabolic alkalosis
promotes magnesium
reabsorption Meanwhile,
loop diuretics, any kind of
diuretics, excess calcium
and excess magnesium will
cause a decrease of it because
you want to promote their
loss, right? Too much more,
you want to get rid of it.
And the same thing occurs
in distal collecting duct,
if you want to, you know.
So, again, a lot of the
mechanisms of calcium
is the same mechanism
you find for magnesium.
Okay, and the last ion we'll
talk about is phosphate.
So, phosphate is the most
important of calcium. And
what makes it fun, it's
because calcium and phosphate
go hand in hand in
terms of the regulation,
because they're both part
of this mongo protein
hydroxyapatite, which is the
major mineral that we find in
bone. So you can see that
we're constantly making
and resorbing bone to making
sure that our exocelular
potassium concentrations
are tightly controlled.
A majority of the
phosphate we get is through
our diet, but we also
excrete a lot in our food.
And you know where
the phosphate is
in our diet, red
meat, a lot of it.
And you find it in
the form of ATP.
That's where we get
most of our phosphate.
And again, the amount that's
filtered and excreted is
the same amount that's
absorbed, 900 milligrams per
day. We lose about, again,
we want to keep this tight.
Um,
phosphates are
higher in children,
and take a wild guess why.
Again, we're not
doing Socratic because
this is Zoom, but
because kids are growing.
So total levels are higher in
children than they
are in adults.
Again, soft tissue
phosphates are different,
they're more, you know,
soft tissue phosphates are
basically phosphates we
use for nucleic acids,
right, for phosphoproteins,
for phospholipids.
So all our tissues will
have phosphates bound to
other chemicals in order
for daily activities.
So where do we get
phosphate regulation?
This is nice and simple.
It's probably the
easiest way, and
hopefully everything was
as easy as this, right?
You would say that.
All the phosphate reabsorption
occurs in the proximal
convoluted tubule, and it
does so by three phosphate
transporters, the NAP
and the PIT. So the two
isoforms of the NAP, the sodium
phosphate co-transporter.
It takes different molar
values of sodium phosphate,
of sodium and phosphate,
and or actually it's
hydrogen phosphate, you
know, that's the major form
that we have in our plasma
into the cell, and it gets
reabsorbed by mechanisms
that are not very clear.
And any compound that
regulates phosphate
and calcium will act
on it. So vitamin D,
parathyroid hormone,
glucocorticoids, all of
them have regulate
phosphate reabsorption.
and acid-base balance
will also have a role in
it because it traps
phosphates, right? The more
acid you have, the more
dihydrogen phosphate
and phosphoric acid,
which will make the,
their ability to get
reabsorbed different.
Okay, and we come to the
end of this lecture, and
simple enough, you know,
you were feeling horrible,
you had something that had
high amounts of potassium,
cocoa water, coconut
water is famous for that,
a lot of potassium,
bananas, obviously, we
would always tell you,
eat your bananas, and
that could treat the
issues that you felt.
Okay,
the lecture feedback
form, that concludes
this lecture. Next
lecture, we'll talk about
some of the non
-electrolytes, and then we
finalize with acid
base and concentration
abilities of the kidney.
All right, thank you.